Finding Aid of the More Than One Struggle Oral History Project Records, 1939-2004, bulk 1995-1996
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries, Archives Department
More Than One Struggle Oral History Project Records, 1939-2004bulk 1995-1996
Dougherty, Jack
UWM Manuscript Collection 217
4.1 cubic ft. (8 boxes)
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries, Archives Department
Collection consists of oral history interviews conducted by Jack Dougherty during the course of researching his book More Than One Struggle: The Evolution of Black School Reform in Milwaukee. The oral histories consist of audio cassettes, transcripts, correspondence with interviewees, and post-interview notes. The collection also contains Dougherty's research files on related subjects.
While researching his dissertation on African American school reform and activism from the 1930s to the 1990s in Milwaukee, Wisconsin, Jack Dougherty conducted over sixty-five oral history interviews. Most were recorded during the summers of 1995 and 1996, and transcribed within the following year or two. Portions of these stories were included in his book, More Than One Struggle: The Evolution of Black School Reform in Milwaukee.
The oral history project sought to interview and document African Americans who engaged in one or more K-12 school reform movements from the 1930s to the 1990s. Interviewees included individuals who represented different perspectives on the school reform movement due to gender or position within the organization (leading spokesperson versus ordinary participants). Detailed information about Dougherty's interview process, the impact of these interviews on his writing, and similar matters is contained in series 2, in a folder titled "Project Background." This folder also contains detailed information about topics discussed in each interview.
Although the interviews played a significant role in shaping Dougherty's understanding of African American school reform and activism, excerpts from the interviews appear infrequently in the published work. Thus the collection contains a wealth of information to support original research into and writing about this topic.
Scope and content notes of each series are included in the contents list.
The records are arranged into the following series:
Oral History Interviews, 1995-1996
Research Files, 1939-2004
The files are organized alphabetically within each series.
Alternate Format
Selections from this collection are included in the UWM Libraries' digital collection The March On Milwaukee: Civil Rights History Project.
Electronic versions of transcripts for the interviews are also available for use in the reading room. Consult an archivist for more information.
Related Material in the UWM Libraries
Congress of Racial Equality Milwaukee Chapter Records Milwaukee Manuscript Collection 27
James Groppi Papers Milwaukee Manuscript Collection EX Milwaukee Tape 5
Lloyd A. Barbee Papers Milwaukee Manuscript Collection 16 Milwaukee Micro Collection 42
Milwaukee United School Integration Committee Records Milwaukee Manuscript Collection 5
Milwaukee Urban League Records Milwaukee Manuscript Collection EZ Milwaukee Micro Collection 20 Milwaukee Tape 6
National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, Milwaukee Branch Records Milwaukee Manuscript Collection EP
Ray Alexander Papers UWM Manuscript Collection 192
Administrative/Restriction Information
There are no access restrictions on the materials, and the collection is open to all members of the public in accordance with state law.
Jack Dougherty donated the collection to the Archives in October 2004 (accession 2004-022).
Contents List
- 1. Oral History Interviews, 1995-1996
  Series contains oral history interviews, consisting of audio cassettes and transcripts, conducted between 1995-1996 by Jack Dougherty. Interviewees provide insight into Milwaukee school reform activism through their discussions about Coalition of Parents for Quality Education, Committee of One Hundred, CORE (Congress of Racial Equality), Federation of Independent Community Schools, Freedom Schools, MUSIC (Milwaukee United School Integration), Milwaukee Urban League, NAACP (National Association for the Advancement of Colored People), North Division High School, Parents Action Committee for Education (PACE), Sherman Park Community Association, Triple O-Blacks For Two-Way Integration, Urban Day School, and Washington High School. Also included in this series are Dougherty's post-interview notes.
  - Adams, Juanita, and Arlene Johnson
    Juanita Adams and Arlene Johnson were two founders of the Congress of Racial Equality's (CORE) Milwaukee chapter. Topics include their choice to become involved with school integration, differences between CORE and Milwaukee United School Integration Committee (MUSIC), personal experiences with racism including threats of violence, the school boycott of 1964, fellow members of CORE, and gender roles in CORE.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 7, Audio 1-2)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alexander, Ray
    Ray Alexander was Executive Director of the Afro Urban Institute beginning in 1970. He also served as Community Relations Director for the North Town Development and Planning Council. His interview topics include fellow community activists of the late 1960's, the United Community Action Group, and inner city youth employment programming.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 7, Audio 3)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Banks, Phyllis, and Teresa Green
    Phyllis Banks began teaching at Riverside High School in 1962. Theresa Pauline Green, her sister, was a Professor at UC-Berkeley and became involved with Milwaukee from afar. They discuss the teaching of black history at Riverside High School, the school boycott of 1964, racism that Banks faced from Riverside High School's administration, the feeling of unity during the movement, and problems with initial school integration efforts.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 7, Audio 4)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Barbee, Lloyd
    Attorney Lloyd Barbee represented the 18th Assembly District (formerly the 6th District, Milwaukee) in the Wisconsin State Assembly and held numerous offices including in the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) and in the Milwaukee United School Integration Committee (MUSIC). His interview topics include Congress of Racial Equality, the Harold Story Committee in 1963, the NAACP, and his role in education reform in Milwaukee.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 7, Audio 5-6)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Beason, Jake
    Jake Beason, a retired high school teacher, taught at both North Division and Custer High Schools. His interview topics include the early efforts at teaching black history in Milwaukee, the 1967 textbook turn-in, previous unwillingness of Milwaukee Public Schools (MPS) to hire black teachers and the groups which affected change in this area. He also discusses MPS' recruitment efforts at historically black southern colleges, the problems of teaching with inadequate textbooks, and success of black students in integrated schools.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 7, Audio 7)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Beckley, Maurice
    Maurice Beckley was managing editor of the Milwaukee Star newspaper and worked as an industrial engineer at Johnson Controls. In his interview Beckley critiques the Milwaukee United School Integration Committee (MUSIC). Beckley discusses in contrast the Alliance for Better Education and the importance of education in the advancement of African Americans during the 1960's.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 7, Audio 8)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bell, Martha
    Martha Bell worked as a teacher's aide at Wells Junior High School. Her interview topics include her involvement with the Parents Action Committee for Education and the school boycotts of 1964 and 1965. She also discusses the MacDowell school construction protest, the disturbance at Wells over the need to hire black cooks, the Milwaukee Public School system's reluctance to hire teachers from black colleges, problems with busing, and the prevalence of women in the school integration movement.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 7, Audio 9)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Brown, Cecil, Jr., and Loretta Brown
    Cecil Brown Jr. founded Milwaukee's chapter of Congress of Racial Equality (CORE) in 1963 and also served as chairman of the chapter. He also served as Vice-Chairman of Milwaukee United School Integration Committee (MUSIC). Cecil and Loretta Brown discuss de facto segregation, the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People's local fight for the hiring of African American teachers in Milwaukee Public Schools, CORE, and the relationship between CORE and MUSIC.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 7, Audio 10-11)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Caesar, Elsie, M.
    Elsie Caesar was involved with the Coalition to Save North Division in 1979. She discusses the motivations of the group, other's perceptions that they were anti-integration, their eventual success, her politically active daughter, the belief of some that integration wasn't as important as having good teachers, and the busing of her grandchildren in 1979 and 1980.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 7, Audio 12)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Champion, Rev. Leo, Inonia, and Eugene
    Inonia and Rev. Leo Champion came to Milwaukee in 1959. Inonia was a teacher at the Jerusalem Freedom School, and they both were involved with Congress of Racial Equality (CORE) and in the Milwaukee United School Integration Committee (MUSIC) campaign against intact busing. Their interview topics include the effects of intact busing on African American children, the organization and planning of the Milwaukee school boycotts, and the relationships between CORE, MUSIC, and the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP).
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 7, Audio 13-14)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Chancey, Felmers
    Felmers Chancey is a former Milwaukee Police officer who worked with Milwaukee Urban League and the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) in Milwaukee. He reflects on being a policeman during the open housing marches and a member of the Central City Development Corporation during the North Division High School controversy. He also discusses his work on the Milwaukee Public Schools desegregation lawsuit settlement, and explains his opposition to many of the integration reformers of the 1960's.
    - Interview, 1996, Audio cassette (Box 7, Audio 15)
    - Transcript, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Cheeks, Thomas M.
    Thomas M. Cheeks was assigned to teach at Lincoln High School in 1951, making him the first African American to teach secondary public school in Milwaukee. He transferred to school administration in 1964. His interview topics include We-Milwaukee, The Academy Report of 1967, busing of African American children, and The Committee of 34, an organization created in the 1960's to address conditions in Milwaukee.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 7, Audio 16)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Davis, Reginald
    Reginald Davis, a Milwaukee native, attended Riverside, Washington and West Division High Schools. He discusses starting the group BOY (Black Organized Youth) in 1967 as a result of dissatisfaction with the Milwaukee Public Schools, Cynthia Pitts and Lloyd Barbee as mentors of BOY, an incident of teacher brutality at Riverside in 1968, and "walkout" protests with which he was involved.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 7, Audio 17)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - El-Amin, Saleem (formley Jeff Crawford), Mustafa, and Haneefah Hasan, and Muhammad Aleem
    Saleem El-Amin came to Milwaukee when he was 6 years old and attended North Division High School. He later became principle of Clara Muhammad School, an independent Muslim school founded in 1972. This is a group interview, but is mostly conducted with Saleem El-Amin. The interview topics include Clara Muhammad School as an alternative to Lloyd Barbee's call for integration, and the education reform movement as it applied to Milwaukee's African American Muslim community.
    - Interview, 1996, Audio cassette (Box 7, Audio 18)
    - Transcript, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Finlayson, Edith
    Edith Finlayson is a Milwaukee nurse who became involved with the school issue reform because of her children. She discusses the founding of the EB Phillips Daycare Center, her relationship with Lloyd Barbee, her involvement in Milwaukee United School Integration Committee, her children's experience in school, problems finding housing near the better schools, and an incident of racism at University School.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 7, Audio 19-20)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Flowers, Allen
    Allen Flowers moved to Milwaukee to become part of the economic development movement and was director of the North Side Community Design Center. He argued for building North Division High School just west of its current site because the current site disrupted an area of high black home ownership. He also discusses the Northtown Development Committee, Milwaukee's political structure and its effect on the housing movement and urban development.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 7, Audio 21)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Fuller, Howard
    Howard Fuller, a native of Milwaukee, was one of the founding members of the Coalition to Save North Division. His topics include his experiences with school integration issues in Cleveland and being the first black student at Carroll College, the importance of integration for better education, the importance of coalitions for reaching the community, the founding of and opposition to the Coalition to Save North Division, and Lloyd Barbee.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 7, Audio 22-23)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Goens, Geraldine, and Jay Gilmer
    Geraldine Gilmer Goens, a teacher in the Milwaukee Public School system since 1951, comprises the bulk of this interview. Her interview topics include African American teachers having to teach far from their neighborhood schools, and classroom conditions for African American children and teachers. She also discusses teacher education for African Americans at Wisconsin State Teachers College and their policy of forcing African Americans to sign an agreement not to teach secondary school in Milwaukee Public Schools upon graduation.
    - Interview, 1996, Audio cassette (Box 7, Audio 24)
    - Transcript, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Gordon, Grant, and Lucinda Gordon
    Grant Gordon became the first black principal in Milwaukee in 1960 at Garfield High School; Lucinda Gordon was active with the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) in Milwaukee. They share their impressions of the Milwaukee United School Integration Committee's school boycotts in 1964 and 1965, the problems of busing in 1979 and 1980, the Project Rise program for academically struggling schools, and the Lady Pitts program for providing education for pregnant teens.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 7, Audio 25)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Gregg, Rev. B. S.
    Reverend B.S. Gregg was pastor of St. Matthew CME church for several years, and served as treasurer of Milwaukee United School Integration Committee (MUSIC) in 1964. Interview topics include his relationship with Mayor Maier, the Freedom Schools and St. Matthew's role in the school boycott in 1964, and his work with Lloyd Barbee on education reform.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 7, Audio 26)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Hannah, F. Marvin
    F. Marvin Hannah came to Milwaukee in 1955 after leaving the Navy. He discusses his work to enter African American students into apprenticeship programs, the North Division Subsystem, sending his children to Harambee Community School, his time as president of the Milwaukee Alliance of Black School Educators, problems with the initial school desegregation plan for Milwaukee after the 1976 court ruling, and his feelings on magnet schools.
    - Interview, 1996, Audio cassette (Box 7, Audio 27)
    - Transcript, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Harper, Rev. Fred
    Reverend Fred Harper was pastor during the 1960's at King Solomon Church. His interview topics include his experience as a parent transferring his daughter from a predominately black school to a predominately white school, the role of King Solomon Church in the Freedom Schools, the school desegregation lawsuit of 1965, and African American immersion schools as a response to the fight for school integration.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 7, Audio 28)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Harpole, Mildred
    Mildred Harpole worked as a Reading Specialist at Wells Junior High School and Lincoln High School. She discusses teaching at Freedom Schools during 1964 and 1965, problems with Milwaukee Public Schools' busing program, her experience growing up in segregated schools in Baltimore and Cleveland, and running for the Milwaukee School Board in 1971.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 7, Audio 29)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Harpole, Reuben, Jr.
    Reuben Harpole Jr, helped develop many Milwaukee institutions such as the Black Holocaust Museum, UWM's Center for Urban Community Development and the Harambee Community Development Corporation. His interview topics include a personal account of white flight in the Harambee neighborhood, boycotts of Boston Store and Gimbles, Milwaukee Star's role in disseminating information to the African American community, Concerned Citizens for Quality Education, and key community leaders in the fight for equality in education.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 7, Audio 30)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Harris, Robert
    Robert Harris is a Milwaukee native who began working for Milwaukee Public Schools in 1954. He discusses his time as a football coach at North Division High School starting in 1964, the inequities that existed between North Division and other high schools in the area, the Milwaukee United School Integration Committee in 1964 and 1965, and his views on what providing a quality education entails.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 7, Audio 31-32)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Harris, Vada
    Vada Harris discusses her activities as Secretary of Wisconsin's National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Youth Council and as a member of the Youth Council Commandos, teaching black history in the Freedom Schools, and marching for open housing. She also attended Riverside High School where she led a "textbook turn-in" in 1967 to protest the lack of black history curriculum and instruction.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 7, Audio 33)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Holt, Mikel
    Mikel Holt, a Milwaukee native, is associated with the Milwaukee Community Journal from 1967 to the present as a reporter, editor and associate publisher. Holt discusses the stance of the African American community in regards to school integration, the Community Journal's criticism of desegregation in 1976-1977, black politicians who were involved in the school movement, and school choice issues taking place in Milwaukee during the 1980's.
    - Interview, 1996, Audio cassette (Box 7, Audio 34)
    - Transcript, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Hopkins, Fred
    Fred Hopkins was born and raised in Milwaukee and attended North Division High School and Clifford McKissick Community School. He was a member of North Division's School Community Site Committee and the first vice-president of Blac-A-Vention, a group of inner-city activists who lobbied for black representation on the Milwaukee Public School board. His interview topics include his experience of intact busing as a student, participating in a school boycott, attending Clifford McKissick Community School, and the state of the Milwaukee Public Schools in the 1960's and early 1970's.
    - Interview, 1996, Audio cassette (Box 7, Audio 35)
    - Transcript, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Jackson, Carolyn
    Carolyn Jackson moved to the Sherman Park neighborhood of Milwaukee in 1975. In 1976 she joined the Sherman Park Community Association Education Committee. She discusses the education committee's focus, working with the Coalition for Peaceful Schools, the push for Metro Milwaukee desegregation in 1975, and being part of the Committee of 100 in 1978.
    - Interview, 1996, Audio cassette (Box 7, Audio 36)
    - Transcript, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Jackson, Gwen
    Gwen Jackson, a community activist with a Milwaukee elementary school named in her honor, served in the 1960's as Chair of the Milwaukee Urban League Family Life Committee. Her interview topics include the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People and the Milwaukee Urban League's role in Milwaukee education reform, a critique of Father Groppi's leadership of Milwaukee youth, and Lloyd Barbee's role as a lawyer in the struggle for equality in Milwaukee.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 7, Audio 37)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Jackson, Harold B., Jr.
    Harold B. Jackson Jr. was elected to the Milwaukee School Board in 1970 after serving as an Assistant District Attorney in Milwaukee. He discusses growing up under segregation in Washington D.C., the decision to end the intact busing program in Milwaukee, the decision to reinstate teacher Jake Beason in 1971, the desegregation lawsuit against the school board and the 1976 decision in that suit.
    - Interview, 1996, Audio cassette (Box 7, Audio 38-39)
    - Transcript, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Jeter, Maxine
    Maxine Jeter, a member of Milwaukee United School Integration Committee in the 1960's, helped organize protests at St. Boniface Church. Her interview topics include Father Groppi at St. Boniface Church and in the local civil rights movement. She also discusses Lloyd Barbee's lawsuit against the Milwaukee School Board, the Catholic Family Movement at St. Boniface, and provides a detailed explanation of intact busing.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 7, Audio 40)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Johnson, Ronald
    Ronald Johnson, a Milwaukee native, graduated from Custer High School in 1969 and taught Black History at Harambee Community School beginning in 1971. He discusses his time as a member of the Milwaukee Black Panthers, teaching at Harambee, and his opinions on the pressure placed on Milwaukee Public Schools to teach black history.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 7, Audio 41)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Jones, Nellie
    Nellie Jones was secretary of Parents Action Committee for Education (PACE) and a member of the 20th Street School's Parent Teacher Association. Her interview topics include the creation and ending of PACE as well as Lloyd Barbee's assistance with it. She also discusses sending her children to Lancaster Elementary School while it was predominantly white as an alternative to intact busing.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 8, Audio 42)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Jones, Walter